*******************************************************************************
        SRAC2003 ; The Integrated Neutronics Calculation Code System
*******************************************************************************
SRAC is a integrated neutronics calculation code system applicable to core
analyses of various types of reactors. Since the publication of JAERI-1302 for
the revised SRAC in 1986, a number of additions and modifications have been 
made for nuclear data libraries and programs. Thus, the new version SRAC2003
has been completed.

The system consists of several nuclear data libraries (ENDF/B-VI, JENDL-3.3,
JEF-3.0 and so on), five modular codes integrated into SRAC2003; collision
probability calculation module(PIJ) for 16 types of lattice geometries, Sn
transport calculation modules(ANISN, TWOTRAN), diffusion calculation
modules(TUD, CITATION) and an optional code (COREBN) for core burn-up
calculations and fuel managements, which has been mainly used for research
reactors in JAERI.

In this version, many new functions and data are implemented to support nuclear
design studies of advanced reactors. SRAC95 is available on scalar or vector
computers with the UNIX operating system or its similar ones (Linux/FreeBSD).

*******************************************************************************
                       Users Manual
*******************************************************************************

(1) Okumura K.,Kaneko K. and Tsuchihashi K.:"SRAC95 ; General Purpose Neutronics
    Code System", JAERI-Data/Code 96-015 (1996) (in Japanese).

(2) Tsuchihashi K.,Ishiguro Y.,Kaneko K. and Ido M.:"Revised SRAC Code System",
    JAERI 1302 (1986). (in English but for old version SRAC)

*******************************************************************************
                       Messages from Developers
*******************************************************************************

(1) We have no responsibility to any troubles in installation or execution
    of SRAC.
(2) When you find some errors in SRAC, please tell us the situation.

*******************************************************************************
                        Structure of SRAC File
*******************************************************************************
   
SRAC         : directory for the SRAC code
      -bin   : directory for SRAC load modules
      -cmnd  : directory for private command (set path in .cshrc)
      -lib   : directory for libraries for SRAC
          -burnlibT  : directory for burnup chain libraries
      -obj   : directory for object modules 
          -SCall     : scalar objects
          -VPpart    : vector objects (only for vector processors)
      -smpl  : directory for sample problems
          -shr       : directory for shell-script and input data
          -outp      : directory for output data
      -src   : directory for source programs
           -srac     : directory for main part of SRAC
           -pij      : directory for Pij part (used also in ASMBURN)
           -cit      : directory for CITATION part (used also in COREBN)
           -burn     : directory for cell burn-up part
           -read     : directory for PDS access part (used also in ASMBURN)
           -common   : common programs (used also in ASMBURN, and COREBN)
           -plot     : directory for plotter part
           -extnl    : directory for system-dependent part
           -sracvp   : directory for vector sources (only for vector processors)
           -citvp    : directory for vector sources (only for vector processors)
           -inc      : directory for include files
      -tmp   : directory for temporary files (work directory)
      -tool  : directory for installation tools
           -install  : directory for SRAC installer
                  -SysDpnd     : directory for system-dependent pre-processors
                      -{*}/PrepInst.sh: system(*)-dependent pre-processor
                      -{*}/lmmake     : template for SRAC/tool/lmmake
                      -Common  : template for SRAC/tool/lmmake (scalar machines)
                  -PrepRset.sh : Uninstaller for pre-processed data
                  -UtilInst.sh : Installer for utility programs
                  -UtilRset.sh : Uninstaller for utility programs
                  -DataInst.sh : Installer for Bickley function table
                  -DataRset.sh : Uninstaller for Bickley function table
                  -ProgInst.sh : Installer for load module
                  -ProgRset.sh : Uninstaller for objects and load modules
                  -OutpRset.sh : Uninstaller for calculated data
                  -menu        : directory for menu of installer
                  -help        : directory for help information
                      -help*.txt      : help information (general)
                      -help.PC1       : help information for PC/AT
                  -custom      : directory for custom-installation menu 
           -kintab   : directory for production of Bickley function table
           -lmmake   : directory for production of load modules
                       this is generated by pre-processor(SysDpnd/*/PrepInst.sh)
                       * : system type = ews-hp, ews-sun, facom-vpp, nec-sx ..
                  -lmmk.sh     : shellscript to produce SRAC load module
           -permit   : directory for tools to permit SRAC to other users
           -else     : directory for other tools (source conversion, etc.)
                  -F77conv     : converter for FORTRAN compile driver and option
                  -VPconv      : converter for vector control statements
                  -IncConv     : converter for include statements
                  -mkmk        : directory for Makefile generator
      -util  : directory for utility programs
           -pdscnvt  : directory for PDStoTXT or TXTtoPDS
           -pdsmdl   : directory for PDSMDL (modular subroutine package)
           -admin    : directory of utilities for administrator of SRAC 
      -admin : directory only for developers of SRAC

*******************************************************************************
                           How to Install SRAC Code
*******************************************************************************
(1) Required Disk Capacity for Installation (No Library Data)
    before Installation : about  5 M-bytes    (now occupied)
    after  Installation : about 10-17-M bytes (depends on system)  
    Note: more large capacity is necessary during installation.

(2) Fisrt of All
    Set the SRAC file in the directory you like.
    e.g. /home/okumura/code/JAERI/SRAC
    You can change the name of the top directory (e.g. SRAC => srac-code)

    Suggested setting of ".cshrc" or ".login" file for convenient use of SRAC :
    e.g.      set path=($HOME/SRAC/cmnd $path)
          or  cp SRAC/cmnd/*  $HOME/bin (your private comannd directory)
    Especially, commands "dir" and "files" in SRAC/cmnd will be very 
    convenient to manage many library data of SRAC.

(3) Before Installation
    Pre-processor must be executed in the main menu of @PunchMe.
    The pre-processor will generates system-dependent source programs,
    makefiles, and shell-scripts to generate load modules.
    The pre-processor will ask you machine type you are now using, then select
    the appropriate number in the menu.

    If you can not find the machine type in the menu, select "You don't know
    who I am". Then, you can change the compile driver name (e.g. f77) and
    compile options by yourself. However, the function to get date, real-time,
    and cpu-time will be suppressed. Although they are not effective for 
    calculated resuts, the lack of the last function restricts restart
    calculatins. Rewrite the source program( /SRAC/src/extnl/uclckm.f), if you
    want.

(4) Installation of SRAC
    In the installation menu of @PunchMe, the following programs and data 
    can be installed.
    1) Utility Programs : binary file manager
    2) Bickley function table : binary data which is used in the collision 
                                probability calculation in SRAC.
    3) SRAC load module : will be generated in the directory SRAC/bin.
    Before the installation of the Bickley function data, the utility 
    programs must be installed.
    Background job will be used except for the utility installation. 
    Messages will be written in the directory SRAC/tmp/. Check them 
    carefully and remove them.
    When the installation failed, try again after you change the Fortran
    compile options or compiler itself. You can see details in the custom-
    installation menu under the installation menu.

(5) Required installation time (depend on compilers and machines)
    about 1 minute       for the utility programs,
    about 15-60 minutes  for the SRAC load module,
    about 1 minite       for the Bickley function table

(6) Manual Installation
    In the cases when the automatic installation by @PunchMe does not work well
    or CPU time of direct job execution is shortly limited, 
    copy the following installation shell-scripts ;
      SRAC/tool/install/UtilInst.sh (utility programs),
      SRAC/tool/install/ProgInst.sh (SRAC load module),
      SRAC/tool/install/DataInst.sh (Bickley function table),
    and change them as you like for manual installation.

(7) Note for Users of FACOM-VPP500 Machines
    In the FACOM-VPP500, data types are different in the front-end processor
    (M,EBCDIC) and in the back-end processor(IEEE,ASCII). Therefore, bainary
    data must be generated in the back-end processor by a batch job.
    The installation of the Bickley function table should not be done in the
    menu of @PunchMe. Install it by yourself as a batch job using the shell-
    script ; SRAC/tool/install/DataInst.sh.

(8) Uninstallation
    All installed data can be deleted selectively in the uninstallation menu of
    @PunchMe. If you failed the installation process, execute the uninstaller
    and try again after you remove the causes of troubles. By using the 
    uninstaller, this file can be recoverd to the initial condition. Therefore,
    you can install without any hesitations.

(9) Library Data
    Any librares for SRAC are not included in this file. They are prepared 
    as external files ; SRACLIB-JDL32, SRACLIB-EDFB4, SRACLIB-JEF22, ....
    To install these library data, use the installer equipped in each
    library file.

(10)Test Run
    After all installations (including library), try to run sample problems 
    and check output data.

    %cd SRAC/smpl/shr
    %Test.sh               (wait for a few time)
    %cd SRAC/smpl/outp
    %vi {file-name}   (confirm output results)
    Other samples may take a lot of time.
    Sample output result in SRAC/smpl/outp is based on the JENDL-3.2 library.
    
    The execution tests have been done on the following machines in JAERI.
    -----------------------------------------------------------------------
    Tested Machine  :  OS              : FORTRAN Compiler       : Note
    -----------------------------------------------------------------------
    HP9000/735      : HP-UX9.07        : HP-UX9.0               : EWS
    Sun Sparc 20    : SunOS 4.1.3      : Sparc 2.01 in Sola.1.1 : EWS
    Sun Sparc 20    : SunOS 4.1.3      : Sparc 3.0  in Sola.1.1 : EWS
    IBM AIX RS/6000 : AIX              : AIX FORTRAN            : EWS / SP
    FACOM AP-3000   : UltarSPARC with Solaris 2.5.1             : Scalar-Paral
    FACOM M-780     : MSP/EX           : FORTRAN77EX            : Scalar
    FACOM GS-8400   : MSP/EX           : FORTRAN77EX            : Scalar
    FACOM VP-2600   : MSP/EX           : FORTRAN77EX/VP         : Vector
    FACOM VPP500/42 : UNIX System V 4.0: UXP/M VPP FORTRAN77EX  : Vector-Paral
    Monte4(NEC SX3) : Monte-UX         : FORTRAN77/M4           : Vector-Paral
    PC/AT Compatible: Linux(redhatV4.2): f2c + gcc (GNU)        : pentium-II
    PC/AT Compatible: Linux(redhatV4.2): g77 + gcc (GNU)        : pentium-II
    -----------------------------------------------------------------------
    *single CPU Job for parallel computers (Parallel job is not supproted)
    -----------------------------------------------------------------------

    In some computers, error message by underflow may be appeaed, but it is
    not effective to calculated results. However, overflow causes significant
    errors to results.
    
(11)Permitting of the SRAC to Other Users
    Execute the following shell-scripts if necessary.
    SRAC/tool/permit/usrpmt.sh (programs, data, utilities for SRAC execution)
    SRAC/tool/permit/srcpmt.sh (source programs)

(12)Others
    The SRAC load module generated by the installer requires program memory 
    of about 24 M-bytes for scalar computers or 44 M-bytes for vector 
    computers.(These are strongly depend on compilers and options.)
    If you want to change the size of program memory, edit the include files 
    in SRAC/src/inc/*/MAINSINC,READPINC.., as you like. And generale a new
    load module using the shell-scripts in SRAC/tool/lmmake/.

    The default installer (ProgInst.sh) do not keep any object files. If you
    want to keep them in SRAC/obj, use the shell-scripts in 
    SRAC/tool/lmmake/objmk/.

*******************************************************************************
                         Consultant
*******************************************************************************

    Keisuke OKUMURA

    Department of Nuclear Energy System,
    Japan Atomic Energy Research Institute (JAERI)
    Tokai-mura, Naka-gun, Ibaraki-ken, 319-1195  Japan

    Telephone : +81 29 282 5321
    (in Japan)   (029) 282 5321
    Telefax   : +81 29 282 6122
    (in Japan)   (029) 282 6122
    E-mail    : okumura@mike.tokai.jaeri.go.jp
    Home page : http://hachi.tokai.jaeri.go.jp/

*******************************************************************************
